<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Tools | Yabage]]></title>
  <link href="http://pierre-jean.baraud.fr/blog/categories/tools/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://pierre-jean.baraud.fr/"/>
  <updated>2016-07-18T09:18:21+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://pierre-jean.baraud.fr/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Pierre-Jean Baraud]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[pierre-jean@baraud.fr]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Introduction to Isometric 3D]]></title>
    <link href="http://pierre-jean.baraud.fr/blog/2014/05/13/3d-iso-introduction/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-13T16:09:50+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://pierre-jean.baraud.fr/blog/2014/05/13/3d-iso-introduction</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/images/iso/iso-result-mini.png" title="" ></p>

<p>You want to create a nice graphic presentation, but you don&rsquo;t know anything about design? You need to create some game graphic elements, but you&rsquo;re really bad at drawing?</p>

<p>Isometric 3D allows you to create really neat and fun elements without knowing anything about design or art. In a few steps you can obtain really nice results.</p>

<!-- More -->


<h2>A simple square</h2>

<p>Let&rsquo;s try to create a square in isometric projection.</p>

<h3>The editor</h3>

<p>I will use the great vector graphics editor <a href="http://www.inkscape.org/">Inkscape</a>, that I have been fond of for years.
Inkscape is free, open-source, multi-platform (Windows, Mac, Linux) and uses the standard format SVG. Many browser can open directly SVG files.</p>

<p>Vector graphics allows you to draw &ldquo;shapes&rdquo; instead of &ldquo;pixels&rdquo;, so you can zoom infinitely without losing precision. Another well known vector graphic editor is Adobe Illustrator.</p>

<p>My instructions will be for Inkscape, but the principles can be applied in any other vectorial or bitmap editor.</p>

<h3>Simple square</h3>

<p>Let&rsquo;s see how to draw a simple square in isometric projection. Open Inkscape and follow these instructions:</p>

<ul>
<li>Select the <strong>rectangle tool</strong> on the left (<strong>F4</strong> on Linux)</li>
<li>Maintain the key <strong>Ctrl</strong> pressed and draw the square. <em>Ctrl</em> will maintain proportions to obtain a square.</li>
</ul>


<p> <img src="/images/iso/iso-screen-01.png"></p>

<ul>
<li>Then, select the <strong>shape edition tool</strong> (<strong>F2</strong>) or click once in your square to enable the shape modification.</li>
<li>Select the upper node and while maintaining <strong>Ctrl</strong> key, skew the square 2 steps to the right. Another method is using the Transform dialog (menu <strong>Object/Transform</strong> or <strong>Shift+Ctrll+M</strong>) and skew horizontally by 30째.</li>
</ul>


<p> <img src="/images/iso/iso-screen-02.png"></p>

<ul>
<li>Finally, Select again the <strong>shape edition tool</strong> (<strong>F2</strong>), and while maintaining the <strong>Ctrl</strong> key, rotate 2 steps to the right. Another method is to use the Transform dialog and rotate by 30째.</li>
</ul>


<p> <img src="/images/iso/iso-screen-03.png"></p>

<p>You now have a nice square in isometric perspective.</p>

<h3>Add Text</h3>

<p>All transformation done to the square can be applied to text too. As a consequence following previous steps:</p>

<ul>
<li>Select <strong>Text tool</strong> (<strong>F8</strong>), and write something.</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="/images/iso/iso-screen-04.png"></p>

<ul>
<li>Skew to the right by 30째.</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="/images/iso/iso-screen-05.png"></p>

<ul>
<li>Rotate to the right by 30째</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="/images/iso/iso-screen-06.png"></p>

<p>You now have shapes and text on the same perspective.</p>

<h3>Add other faces</h3>

<p>By changing the direction of skew or rotation, you can add shapes on the 2 others plans of isometric projection.</p>

<ul>
<li>Create another rectangle</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="/images/iso/iso-screen-07.png"></p>

<ul>
<li>Skew it to the left this time</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="/images/iso/iso-screen-08.png"></p>

<ul>
<li>Rotate it to the right</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="/images/iso/iso-screen-09.png"></p>

<ul>
<li>Notice that if you want to resize your square once on a isometric plan, you can use the square tool once your square selected (or press <strong>F4</strong>) and you&rsquo;ll be able to resize it in the plan by grabbing the corners.</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="/images/iso/iso-screen-10.png"></p>

<ul>
<li>You do the same with the other rectangle, but by skewing it to the right and rotating it to the left</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="/images/iso/iso-screen-11.png"></p>

<p><img src="/images/iso/iso-screen-12.png"></p>

<p><img src="/images/iso/iso-screen-13.png"></p>

<p>By playing with the colors of the different squares, you can obtain a nice impression of volume, without effort or knowledge.</p>

<h3>Be creative</h3>

<p>You can apply this to disc shapes as well and create complete world in isometric projection!</p>

<p><img src="/images/iso/iso-example.png"></p>

<p>Be aware, though, that this method isn&rsquo;t an efficient way to create graphs for report. You can find many specialized tools dedicated to this task. But by drawing from scratch you have a total freedom on the result. Your imagination is your only limit!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
